<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</title>
    <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Chamber of Commerce</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/acc_lunch2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2023 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/acc_lunch2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reforming Canada&#39;s federal health-care funding arrangements</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/fiscal-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/fiscal-health/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rise (And Fall?) of Inflation in Canada: A Detailed Analysis of Its Post-Pandemic Experience</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/inflation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/inflation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conflict of Interest Disclosure</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/post/conflict/conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/post/conflict/conflict/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aeaweb.org/journals/policies/disclosure-policy&#34;&gt;American Economic Association&lt;/a&gt; urges its members and other economists to disclose potential conflicts of interest through financial support (whether in monetary or non-monetary forms), paid or unpaid positions as officers, directors, or board members of non-profit or for-profit organizations, and if other interested third parties have financial, ideological, or political stakes in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a best efforts disclosure based on the most recent five years of activity. More detail around my past professional affiliations, associations, and activities are listed on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/files/CV.pdf&#34;&gt;my CV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sources-of-financial-support&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sources of Financial Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the AEA disclosure policy, authors “should identify each interested party from whom he or she has received significant financial support, summing to at least $10,000 in the past three years, in the form of consultant fees, retainers, grants and the like.” I report these below, separating ongoing sources from one-time ad-hoc sources. For completeness, I also report potentially relevant minor sources of financial support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Calgary (2012-Present): amounts disclosed publicly according to Government of Alberta regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Tax Foundation (2020-Present): stipend for services as co-director of &lt;em&gt;Finances of the Nation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial support through various grants from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (individually listed on my CV)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funds cover research expenses, primarily graduate student support, and no personal financial benefit results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ad-Hoc (Past Five Years)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macdonald-Laurier Institute (2022): research paper on internal trade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Canada (2020): research and analysis of interprovincial trade costs and policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of British Columbia (2020): research contributions to the BC Basic Income Panel (report public)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yukon Government (2017): member of the financial advisory panel (report public)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minor (Past Five Years)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pearson Canada (2023): textbook revisions and data updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C.D. Howe Institute (2020; 2023): research papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Canada (2022-23): advisory services on internal trade policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Myers LLP (2022-23): expert advice to the Alberta Provincial Court Judges and Applications Judges 2021 Compensation Commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macdonald-Laurier Institute (2023): referee report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McGraw Hill Education (2022): textbook revisions and data updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fraser Institute (2016-2023): referee reports and occasional author fees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2020-21): services to the Ministry of Jobs, Economy and Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Ontario (2021): research and analysis of interprovincial trade costs and policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Queen’s University Institute on Trade Policy (2020): presentation on interprovincial trade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Institute for Fiscal Studies and Democracy (2020): research related to federal transfer arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Economics Association (2019): Vanderkamp Prize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parliamentary Budget Office (2019): one-day course on federal-provincial transfers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2019): review of internal economic analysis of carbon pricing policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pearson Canada (2018): produce educational materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Toronto, Munk School of Global Affairs and Public Policy (2018): &lt;em&gt;Ontario 360&lt;/em&gt; report on climate policy for Ontario&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2017): analysis related to large emitter carbon pricing policy design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasional author fees for contributions to &lt;em&gt;The Hub&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CBC&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Macleans&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alberta Views&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;affiliations&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Affiliations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current Professional Associations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professor, University of Calgary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Fellow, The School of Public Policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-Director, Finances of the Nation, &lt;em&gt;Canadian Tax Journal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, The University of Calgary Faculty Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, The Alberta Gambling Research Institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member, Canadian Economics Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member, American Economics Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Affiliations and Appointments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Editorial Advisor, &lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Economics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, ActiveCITY Calgary (2019-20)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the C.D. Howe COVID-19 Crisis Business Continuity and Trade Working Group (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the Government of Alberta Market Access Task Force (2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the Calgary Chamber of Commerce Municipal Election Advisory Team (2017)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;additional-disclosures&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Disclosures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asset Disclosure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various equity and bond holdings, largely within broadly-diversified exchange traded funds. Minor holdings of individual corporate equities within the Canadian financial and energy sectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Activity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am not a member of any political party at any level of government. Occasional (unpaid) advice and analysis has been provided to individual candidates, office holders, or staff on an ad-hoc basis representing the full spectrum of political parties in Alberta and Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right to Review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No organization has a right to review or edit my published work, except when they acted as the publisher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liberalizing internal trade through mutual recognition: A legal and economic analysis</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/mli_trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/mli_trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Canada, provincial and territorial governments have constitutionally enshrined powers that give them considerable jurisdiction over the standards, rules, regulations, and certifications that govern goods and services. These regulatory divergences can and do affect interprovincial trade by making it difficult for goods, services, labour, and capital to flow across borders. These barriers can make it more expensive for consumers in one region to purchase goods and services produced in another, and as a result increase costs and lower Canada&amp;rsquo;s overall productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper examines possible approaches to easing these trade frictions and recommends serious consideration of &amp;ldquo;mutual recognition,&amp;rdquo; a framework wherein an item of commerce that meets the regulatory requirements of one provincial or territorial government is deemed to automatically satisfy the requirements of another. Simply put, mutual recognition requires a host province to accept the standards set out by the province from which the good or service originates. As a result, mutual recognition can lessen the compliance burdens of goods and service providers and eliminate duplicative testing which makes it a powerful tool for eliminating policy-relevant interprovincial trade costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic implications of internal trade costs in Canada are significant. Currently, the volume of trade across provincial and territorial borders is equivalent to nearly 18 percent of Canada&amp;rsquo;s GDP. And in certain regions, such as the prairie provinces, Atlantic provinces, or the three territories, internal trade is an even larger proportion of GDP. Meanwhile, trade costs are relatively high, averaging between 8 to 22 percent (depending on the calculation method) when all goods and services are included. Clearly such costs can meaningfully detract from overall productivity and the living standards of Canadians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the approaches to internal trade liberalization, mutual recognition may go furthest towards easing policy-relevant trade barriers. In its extreme form, mutual recognition would allow any good, service, or professional credential to automatically be considered compliant in any given province if it is already compliant in another. In this situation, there would be no differences in rules or regulations, and therefore no interprovincial costs beyond time, fuel, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring internal trade costs in Canada is a challenge because the barriers are not usually explicit charges placed on cross-border transactions. Instead, they represent the costs of complying with rules, regulations, standards, and certifications that vary from one province to another. This paper uses two methods to estimate the magnitude of such unobservable trade costs: an inferential approach that calculates an estimate of costs from the observed pattern of trade based on the Head-Ries Index of trade costs and a model of Canada&amp;rsquo;s economy that incorporates the latest available date (from 2018) to estimate the economic effects of internal trade costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond estimating the scale of the trade cost reductions that mutual recognition could achieve, this paper also estimates the potential economic gains that could result. We find that Canada&amp;rsquo;s economy could increase by between 4.4 and 7.9 percent over the long-term - a significant gain of between $110 and $200 billion per year, equivalent to between $2900 and $5100 per capita - if internal trade barriers are eliminated by mutual recognition policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential economic benefits for Canada from adopting mutual recognition policies are large, but there are important trade-offs to consider. Trade liberalization requires that resources, production, and employment shift across sectors and even across regions. Sectors in one province that may not survive competition with lower-cost imports may shrink while sectors that see an increase in export volumes may expand. The same is true across regions. Workers in one location may move to another in response to changes in wages and prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our model suggests that between 1.3 and 1.7 percent of Canada&amp;rsquo;s workforce would migrate across provinces in response to eliminating internal trade costs. In the long-run, these moves are productivity enhancing for the overall economy but are not costless in the short-run for the individuals involved. Such moves may be particularly costly if retraining is required. These adjustment costs are not captured in our estimates of the economic effect of trade liberalization but are nonetheless critical for policy-makers to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such large opportunities for additional internal trade liberalization in Canada and the consequent economic and productivity benefits that may result, however, these challenges may not be insurmountable. Pursuing mutual recognition policies within specific areas, such as trucking regulations, food safety, or financial services, may be appropriate. Whatever the best route forward, interest among governments to improve economic growth and liberalize trade may be higher today than any point in recent memory. And mutual recognition should be an important part of the policy conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Long Slide Towards Fiscal Reckoning: Managing Alberta&#39;s Finances in an Age of Decline</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/blue_storm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/blue_storm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Edited by Duane Bratt, Richard Sutherland, and David Taras&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About the Book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first scholarly analysis of the 2019 Alberta Election, which led to the victory of Jason Kenney&amp;rsquo;s United Conservative Party, and of the UCP&amp;rsquo;s first years in government.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the United Conservative Party, under the leadership of Jason Kenney, unseated the New Democratic Party to form the provincial government of Alberta. A restoration of conservative power in a province that had seen the Progressive Conservatives win every election from 1971-2015, UCP quickly began to make political waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first scholarly analysis of the 2019 election and the first years of the UCP government, with special focus on the path of Jason Kenney&amp;rsquo;s rise to, and fall from, provincial political power. It opens with an examination of the election from a number of vantage points, including the campaign, polling, and online politics. It provides fascinating insight into internal UCP politics with chapters on the divisions within the party, gender and the UCP, and the symbolism of Kenney&amp;rsquo;s famous blue pickup truck. Explorations of oil and gas policy, the Energy War Room, Alberta&amp;rsquo;s budgets, health care, education, the public sector, Alberta&amp;rsquo;s cultural industries, and more provide unprecedented insight into the actions, motivations, and impacts of Kenney&amp;rsquo;s UCP Government in power. Contributions from top political watchers, journalists, and academics provide a wide range of methods and perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concluding with a survey of the impacts of COVID-19 in Alberta and a comparison between Jason Kenney and Doug Ford, Blue Storm is essential reading for everyone interested in Alberta politics and the tumultuous first years of the UCP government. Providing key insights from perspectives across the political spectrum, this book is a captivating deep-dive into an unprecedented party, its often controversial politics, and its unforgettable leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With Contributions By:&lt;/strong&gt; Duane Bratt, Brad Clark, Brooks DeCillia, Roger Epp, Doug King, Jonathan Malloy, Tyler Nagel, Chaseten Remillard, Jean-Sebastien Rioux, Peter Ryan, Anthony M. Sayers, Gillian Steward, David K. Stewart, Richard Sutherland, Melanee Thomas, Graham Thomson, Trevor Tombe, Kate Toogood, Charles F. Webber, Jared Wesley, Lori Williams, and Lisa Young&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Federal Equalization Program as a Controversial and Contested Policy Success</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/eqsuccess/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/eqsuccess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 12 in E. Lindquist, M. Howlett, G. Skogstad, G. Tellier, P. &amp;rsquo;t Hart. eds. Policy Success in Canada: Cases, Lessons, Challenges. Oxford University Press, 2022.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created in 1957, the federal equalization program addresses the issue of horizontal fiscal imbalance and, more specifically, seeks to reduce interprovincial disparities in fiscal capacity. Excluding the three territories, which fall under Territorial Formula Financing, the equalization program allocates payments to the provinces whose fiscal capacity falls under a national average. This means that, in contrasts to the two other large federal transfers, the Canada Health Transfer and the Canada Social Transfer, equalization does not make annual payments to all the provinces. Simultaneously, since the creation of the program, all the provinces have received equalization payments for at least a few years. In 2019-2020, equalization payments to the five recipient  provinces (Manitoba, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, Prince Edward Island and Quebec) totaled nearly 20 billion dollars. In comparison, that fiscal year, the Canada Health Transfer and the Canada Social Transfer allocated about 40 and 15 billion dollars respectively to provinces and territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, we argue that equalization policy has been successful in reducing interprovincial inequalities while preserving the autonomy of the provinces, as equalization payments have no strings attached. This capacity to reconcile provincial autonomy with egalitarian goals rooted in shared social citizenship is featured in section 36(2) of the 1982 Constitutional Act: &amp;ldquo;Parliament and the government of Canada are committed to the principle of making equalization payments to ensure that provincial governments have sufficient revenues to provide reasonably comparable levels of public services at reasonably comparable levels of taxation.&amp;rdquo; A comparison with the United States, which does not have a stand-alone equalization program, allows us to show why this program makes a difference in the life of Canadians and in the proper functioning of the federation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may sound surprising to praise equalization policy in a time where strong voices, especially those coming from Alberta and Saskatchewan, are criticizing the program. In our chapter, we review these criticisms and show that many of them are grounded in basic misunderstandings about how equalization works. This gap between the negative discourse about equalization and the effective functioning of the program is a key political challenge our chapter addresses. Simultaneously, we recognize that some criticisms of equalization policy are legitimate, which is why we offer potential policy solutions to address them and improve this effective and important program Canadians should learn more about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fiscal Sustainability and Diverging Fortunes in Atlantic Canada</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/atlantic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/atlantic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Art of Sharing by Mary Janigan</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/art_sharing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/art_sharing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Who Pays for Canada? Edited by E.A. Heaman and David Tough</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/who_pays/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/who_pays/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interprovincial Trade: The real barrier to post-COVID recovery?</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_trade2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_trade2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Panelists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Jared Carlberg&lt;/strong&gt;, Faculty of Agricultural and Food Sciences, University of Manitoba&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Trevor Tombe&lt;/strong&gt;, Research Fellow, The School of Public Policy, University of Calgary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Krystle Wittevrongel&lt;/strong&gt;, Policy Analyst, Montreal Economic Institute&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moderator: &lt;strong&gt;Kara Oosterhuis&lt;/strong&gt;, RealAgriculture&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UC San Diego</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/ucsd2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/ucsd2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University of Victoria</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/uvic2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/uvic2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>York University</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/york2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/york2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s Debatable: Equalization Referendum</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/debatable/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 08:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/debatable/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
