<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</title>
    <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The COVID-19 Crisis and Canadian Federalism</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_federalism/the-covid-19-crisis-and-canadian-federalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_federalism/the-covid-19-crisis-and-canadian-federalism/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The need to review Canada&#39;s Fiscal Stabilization Program for provinces after COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/cwf_whatnow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/cwf_whatnow/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Federal Equalization Program: An Untold and Misunderstood Canadian Success</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/eqsuccess/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/eqsuccess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book chapter in progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created in 1957, the federal equalization program addresses the issue of horizontal fiscal imbalance and, more specifically, seeks to reduce interprovincial disparities in fiscal capacity. Excluding the three territories, which fall under Territorial Formula Financing, the equalization program allocates payments to the provinces whose fiscal capacity falls under a national average. This means that, in contrasts to the two other large federal transfers, the Canada Health Transfer and the Canada Social Transfer, equalization does not make annual payments to all the provinces. Simultaneously, since the creation of the program, all the provinces have received equalization payments for at least a few years. In 2019-2020, equalization payments to the five recipient  provinces (Manitoba, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, Prince Edward Island and Quebec) totaled nearly 20 billion dollars. In comparison, that fiscal year, the Canada Health Transfer and the Canada Social Transfer allocated about 40 and 15 billion dollars respectively to provinces and territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, we argue that equalization policy has been successful in reducing interprovincial inequalities while preserving the autonomy of the provinces, as equalization payments have no strings attached. This capacity to reconcile provincial autonomy with egalitarian goals rooted in shared social citizenship is featured in section 36(2) of the 1982 Constitutional Act: &amp;ldquo;Parliament and the government of Canada are committed to the principle of making equalization payments to ensure that provincial governments have sufficient revenues to provide reasonably comparable levels of public services at reasonably comparable levels of taxation.&amp;rdquo; A comparison with the United States, which does not have a stand-alone equalization program, allows us to show why this program makes a difference in the life of Canadians and in the proper functioning of the federation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may sound surprising to praise equalization policy in a time where strong voices, especially those coming from Alberta and Saskatchewan, are criticizing the program. In our chapter, we review these criticisms and show that many of them are grounded in basic misunderstandings about how equalization works. This gap between the negative discourse about equalization and the effective functioning of the program is a key political challenge our chapter addresses. Simultaneously, we recognize that some criticisms of equalization policy are legitimate, which is why we offer potential policy solutions to address them and improve this effective and important program Canadians should learn more about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finances of the Nation</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/fon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/fon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The main site for the project is at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://financesofthenation.ca/team/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;financesofthenation.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Aggregate Productivity Effect of Labour and Capital Market Distortions in Canada</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/canada_misallocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/canada_misallocation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implications of an Infrastructure Corridor for Alberta&#39;s Economy</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ab_corridor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ab_corridor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advocacy AM: Edmonton Chamber of Commerce</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/yeg_chamber_may2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/yeg_chamber_may2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this edition of Advocacy A.M., we will welcome Trevor Tombe, Associate Professor of Economics at the University of Calgary, to share his insights. He will discuss the depth and scale of the disruption in the labour market and the economy. Then joined by Edmonton Chamber&amp;rsquo;s Director of Advocacy and Outreach, they will dive into the latest data to explore the challenges with reopening and what we know so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following his presentation, you will have an opportunity to ask questions directly to Trevor; bring your queries about the economy, fiscal impact of COVID-19 or anything in between!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please confirm your attendance by Monday, June 1 @ 4 PM.&lt;/strong&gt;
We will be using the Zoom meeting platform for the webinar. A link to join the meeting will be sent out to all registrants 12-24 hours prior to the webinar via email.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Economic diversification - model, myth or mischief?</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MISC Webinar: COVID-19 crisis and its impact on Canada</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/misc_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/misc_covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Regional Distribution of Federal Fiscal Balances: Who Pays, Who Gets and Why It Matters</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/transfers_1961/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/transfers_1961/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Critical Juncture in Fiscal Federalism? Canada&#39;s Response to COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/fiscal_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/fiscal_covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Financing the Future: Options for Long-Run Debt and Spending Sustainability in British Columbia</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bc-fiscal-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bc-fiscal-future/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policy Forum: Expenditures, Efficiency, and Distribution-Advice for Canada&#39;s 43rd Parliament</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/policy_forum/policy-forum-expenditures-efficiency-and-distribution-advice-for-canadas-43rd-parliament/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/policy_forum/policy-forum-expenditures-efficiency-and-distribution-advice-for-canadas-43rd-parliament/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The DNA of New Exporters: Spin-Offs and FDI at the Extensive Margin of Trade</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/dna_exporters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/dna_exporters/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it too early for a report card on UCP performance? Analysing the UCP&#39;s 2nd provincial budget</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_budget2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 09:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_budget2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Panelists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Janet Brown&lt;/strong&gt;, Principal, Janet Brown Opinion Research
&lt;strong&gt;Trevor Tombe&lt;/strong&gt;, Associate Professor, Economics, University of Calgary
&lt;strong&gt;Lisa Young&lt;/strong&gt;, Professor &amp;amp; Director of Graduate Programs, The School of Public Policy
Moderated by, &lt;strong&gt;Rob Breakenridge&lt;/strong&gt;, Radio Host, 770 CHQR
Registration: $20, includes continental breakfast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7:30 a.m. Registration and Breakfast
8:00 a.m. Program
9:30 a.m. Event Concludes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHERE:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Calgary, Downtown Campus
Main Floor Event Centre
906, 8 Ave SW, Calgary&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
