<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</title>
    <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Attitudes, behaviours and barriers to public health measures for COVID-19: a survey to inform public health messaging</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_attitudes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_attitudes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Economic Conditions Index</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/eci/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/eci/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This index compiles monthly data from a variety of sourses to estimate real-time economic conditions in Alberta. It closely follows the Chicago Fed National Activity Index. These estimates will be periodically updated, and typically come with a two to three month lag before all the necessary monthly data is available from Statistics Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download a CSV file of the montly index values &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trevortombe/alberta_eci/raw/master/ECI_Index_Data.csv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implications of an Infrastructure Corridor for Alberta&#39;s Economy</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar_rail/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar_rail/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Who Pays for Canada? Edited by E.A. Heaman and David Tough</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/who_pays/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/who_pays/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Art of Sharing by Mary Janigan</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/art_sharing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/art_sharing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Labour Market Indicators</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/lfs_backup_index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/lfs_backup_index/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;labour-force-survey&#34;&gt;Labour Force Survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each month Statistics Canada releases their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.statcan.gc.ca/eng/survey/household/3701&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Labour Force Survey&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This is the main source of information on the latest labour market trends throughout Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A selection of some of the latest data is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/data/LFS.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Selected statistics for Calgary and Edmonton are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/data/LFS_cma.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;survey-of-payroll-employment-and-hours&#34;&gt;Survey of Payroll, Employment and Hours&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of the latest SEPH data is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/data/SEPH.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Financing the Future: Options for Long-Run Debt and Spending Sustainability in British Columbia</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bc-fiscal-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bc-fiscal-future/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Government Fiscal Sustainability in Canada After COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/esna_dec2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 09:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/esna_dec2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Queen&#39;s Institute on Trade Policy</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/queens_itp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/queens_itp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta&#39;s Opportunity: The Ins, Outs and Benefits of Greater Job Mobility</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/cdhowe_migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/cdhowe_migration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study in Brief&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alberta should open its doors to job seekers with labour mobility reforms that will boost its economic fortunes post-COVID. The province has a unique opportunity to promote economic revival and longterm economic growth by ensuring that it is the most welcoming jurisdiction to talented workers and entrepreneurs from across Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gains from easing labour mobility restrictions are large. In this report, we find that for each 1,000 additional workers that move into Alberta in response to lower migration costs we estimate Alberta&amp;rsquo;s economy grows by 141 million dollars. And if migration costs fall by 1 percent across the board, we estimate gains of nearly 9 billion dollars. Better enabling Canadians to make this choice could provide a crucial support for Alberta&amp;rsquo;s economy at a time of transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though other provinces would benefit from similarly reducing barriers to potential movers, both Alberta and Canada as a whole can gain from unilateral moves by the province to lower the costs for Canadians who might contemplate plying their trade, exercising their profession, or operating their business from Alberta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greater interprovincial mobility under a succession of regional and internal trade agreements has been beneficial and deepened the pool of workers available to Alberta. But obstacles remain for trades people and professionals who would come to Alberta. In particular, there are sometimes significant challenges to having their designation, training, or experience from other provinces seamlessly recognized. Recognizing those credentials, limiting the paperwork required of potential movers, and a more widespread recognition of national certifications and designations, such as those occurring under the Red Seal program, would enhance such mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the study shows that there is a close connection between fostering increased labour mobility and lower barriers to trade in services. For each 1 percent reduction in the cost of importing services from other provinces, we find Alberta&amp;rsquo;s economy grows by nearly 0.1 percent. For a 10 percent reduction in services-trade costs, GDP gains approach 1 percent - equivalent to nearly 3.5 billion dollars per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms we propose would facilitate mobility for employees and entrepreneurs alike. In short, when Canadians can move from one province to another with minimal barriers, the country as a whole benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Provincial Debt Sustainability in Canada: Demographics, Federal Transfers, and COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/ipe_workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/ipe_workshop/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Provincial Debt Sustainability in Canada: Demographics, Federal Transfers, and COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ctj_debt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ctj_debt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The COVID-19 Crisis and Canadian Federalism</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_federalism/the-covid-19-crisis-and-canadian-federalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_federalism/the-covid-19-crisis-and-canadian-federalism/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The need to review Canada&#39;s Fiscal Stabilization Program for provinces after COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/cwf_whatnow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/cwf_whatnow/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Federal Equalization Program: An Untold and Misunderstood Canadian Success</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/eqsuccess/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/eqsuccess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book chapter in progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created in 1957, the federal equalization program addresses the issue of horizontal fiscal imbalance and, more specifically, seeks to reduce interprovincial disparities in fiscal capacity. Excluding the three territories, which fall under Territorial Formula Financing, the equalization program allocates payments to the provinces whose fiscal capacity falls under a national average. This means that, in contrasts to the two other large federal transfers, the Canada Health Transfer and the Canada Social Transfer, equalization does not make annual payments to all the provinces. Simultaneously, since the creation of the program, all the provinces have received equalization payments for at least a few years. In 2019-2020, equalization payments to the five recipient  provinces (Manitoba, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, Prince Edward Island and Quebec) totaled nearly 20 billion dollars. In comparison, that fiscal year, the Canada Health Transfer and the Canada Social Transfer allocated about 40 and 15 billion dollars respectively to provinces and territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, we argue that equalization policy has been successful in reducing interprovincial inequalities while preserving the autonomy of the provinces, as equalization payments have no strings attached. This capacity to reconcile provincial autonomy with egalitarian goals rooted in shared social citizenship is featured in section 36(2) of the 1982 Constitutional Act: &amp;ldquo;Parliament and the government of Canada are committed to the principle of making equalization payments to ensure that provincial governments have sufficient revenues to provide reasonably comparable levels of public services at reasonably comparable levels of taxation.&amp;rdquo; A comparison with the United States, which does not have a stand-alone equalization program, allows us to show why this program makes a difference in the life of Canadians and in the proper functioning of the federation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may sound surprising to praise equalization policy in a time where strong voices, especially those coming from Alberta and Saskatchewan, are criticizing the program. In our chapter, we review these criticisms and show that many of them are grounded in basic misunderstandings about how equalization works. This gap between the negative discourse about equalization and the effective functioning of the program is a key political challenge our chapter addresses. Simultaneously, we recognize that some criticisms of equalization policy are legitimate, which is why we offer potential policy solutions to address them and improve this effective and important program Canadians should learn more about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
