<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</title>
    <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Fiscal and Economic Trajectory of Newfoundland and Labrador</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/mun_cabe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 08:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/mun_cabe/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Senator Paula Simons&#39; Equalization Town Hall</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/eqtownhall/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 12:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/eqtownhall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;YouTube Link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCoC3oZd1Q8-U4NU7a58BX1w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCoC3oZd1Q8-U4NU7a58BX1w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podcast Version: &lt;a href=&#34;https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/alberta-unbound/id1511810939&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/alberta-unbound/id1511810939&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conflict of Interest Disclosure</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/post/conflict/conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/post/conflict/conflict/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aeaweb.org/journals/policies/disclosure-policy&#34;&gt;American Economic Association&lt;/a&gt; urges its members and other economists to disclose potential conflicts of interest through financial support (whether in monetary or non-monetary forms), paid or unpaid positions as officers, directors, or board members of non-profit or for-profit organizations, and if other interested third parties have financial, ideological, or political stakes in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a best efforts disclosure based on the most recent five years of activity. More detail around my past professional affiliations, associations, and activities are listed on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/files/CV.pdf&#34;&gt;my CV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sources-of-financial-support&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sources of Financial Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the AEA disclosure policy, authors “should identify each interested party from whom he or she has received significant financial support, summing to at least $10,000 in the past three years, in the form of consultant fees, retainers, grants and the like.” I report these below, separating ongoing sources from one-time ad-hoc sources. For completeness, I also report potentially relevant minor sources of financial support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Calgary (2012-Present): amounts disclosed publicly according to Government of Alberta regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Tax Foundation (2020-Present): stipend for services as co-director of &lt;em&gt;Finances of the Nation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial support through various grants from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (individually listed on my CV)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funds cover research expenses, primarily graduate student support, and no personal financial benefit results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ad-Hoc (Past Five Years)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Canada (2020): research and analysis of interprovincial trade costs and policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of British Columbia (2020): research contributions to the BC Basic Income Panel (report public)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yukon Government (2017): member of the financial advisory panel (report public)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minor (Past Five Years)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2020-21): services to the Ministry of Jobs, Economy and Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Ontario (2021): research and analysis of interprovincial trade costs and policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Queen’s University Institute on Trade Policy (2020): presentation on interprovincial trade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Institute for Fiscal Studies and Democracy (2020): research related to federal transfer arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C.D. Howe Institute (2020): research paper on interprovincial labour mobility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Economics Association (2019): Vanderkamp Prize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parliamentary Budget Office (2019): one-day course on federal-provincial transfers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2019): review of internal economic analysis of carbon pricing policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pearson Canada (2018): produce educational materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Toronto, Munk School of Global Affairs and Public Policy (2018): &lt;em&gt;Ontario 360&lt;/em&gt; report on climate policy for Ontario&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2017): analysis related to large emitter carbon pricing policy design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fraser Institute (2016-2021): referee reports and occasional author fees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Economics Association (2016): Harry G. Johnson Prize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasional author fees for contributions to &lt;em&gt;CBC&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Hub&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Macleans&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alberta Views&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;affiliations&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Affiliations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current Professional Associations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professor at the University of Calgary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Fellow at The School of Public Policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-Director, Finances of the Nation, &lt;em&gt;Canadian Tax Journal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-Editor, &lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Economics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, The University of Calgary Faculty Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the Canadian Economics Association and the American Economics Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Affiliations and Appointments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, ActiveCITY Calgary (2019-20)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the C.D. Howe COVID-19 Crisis Business Continuity and Trade Working Group (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the Government of Alberta Market Access Task Force (2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the Calgary Chamber of Commerce Municipal Election Advisory Team (2017)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;additional-disclosures&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Disclosures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asset Disclosure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various equity and bond holdings, largely within broadly-diversified exchange traded funds. Minor holdings of individual corporate equities within the Canadian financial and energy sectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Activity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am not a member of any political party at any level of government. Occasional (unpaid) advice and analysis has been provided to individual candidates, office holders, or staff on an ad-hoc basis representing the full spectrum of political parties in Alberta and Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right to Review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No organization has a right to review or edit my published work, except when they acted as the publisher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Sharing: Fiscal relations in the federation</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/cwf2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 12:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/cwf2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a federation the size and scope of Canada, the topic of fiscal inequalities among the provinces is especially fraught. With a referendum on equalization set for the fall in Alberta, the issue has heated up once again. In her book, The Art of Sharing: The Richer versus the Poorer Provinces since Confederation, author Mary Janigan makes the case that a willingness to share financial resources is in fact the real tie that has bound the federation together into the twenty-first century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event brings together a broad range of perspectives: a historian and journalist, a former Attorney General of BC, a former Finance Minister of Saskatchewan, an Alberta economist specializing in fiscal relations and a senior Manitoba intergovernmental official to consider how sharing works - or doesn&amp;rsquo;t work - in Canada, how budget decisions by each order of government across the country affect the services Canadians receive from their governments today and the cost into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join author Mary Janigan and host Colleen Collins, Vice-President Canada West Foundation for a discussion and Q and A session with panelists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suzanne Anton, Former Attorney-General BC and Canada West Foundation Board Member
Trevor Tombe, Associate Professor of Economics, University of Calgary
Kevin Doherty, Managing Director, Saskatchewan Prairie Sky Consulting and Canada West Foundation Board Member
Diane Gray, President &amp;amp; CEO, CentrePort Canada and Canada West Foundation Board Member&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Futures: New fiscal territory, anchors and addressing the debt</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar_fiscal_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar_fiscal_chapter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alberta finds itself in new territory as we emerge from the COVID-19 pandemic. Rising debt levels, falling natural resource revenues, and structural changes to the economy suggests that this time is different. A long-term perspective is required to ensure that the province&amp;rsquo;s economy and government finances remain sustainable into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We invite you to join The School of Public Policy as we host the first in a series of webinars on our Alberta Futures Project. As part of this project we will be releasing a series of reports over the coming weeks in three broad areas: Alberta&amp;rsquo;s Economic Future, Alberta&amp;rsquo;s Fiscal Future and Alberta&amp;rsquo;s Health Care Future. In this webinar, our panel of experts will discuss their recent research into the Fiscal Future of Alberta, and how we can address the challenges currently facing our economy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attitudes, behaviours and barriers to public health measures for COVID-19: a survey to inform public health messaging</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_attitudes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/covid_attitudes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Economic Conditions Index</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/eci/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/eci/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This index compiles monthly data from a variety of sourses to estimate real-time economic conditions in Alberta. It closely follows the Chicago Fed National Activity Index. These estimates will be periodically updated, and typically come with a two to three month lag before all the necessary monthly data is available from Statistics Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download a CSV file of the montly index values &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trevortombe/alberta_eci/raw/master/ECI_Index_Data.csv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implications of an Infrastructure Corridor for Alberta&#39;s Economy</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar_rail/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/spp_webinar_rail/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Who Pays for Canada? Edited by E.A. Heaman and David Tough</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/who_pays/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/who_pays/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implications of an Infrastructure Corridor for Alberta&#39;s Economy</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ab_corridor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ab_corridor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Art of Sharing by Mary Janigan</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/art_sharing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/art_sharing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Labour Market Indicators</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/lfs_backup_index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/lfs_backup_index/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;labour-force-survey&#34;&gt;Labour Force Survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each month Statistics Canada releases their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.statcan.gc.ca/eng/survey/household/3701&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Labour Force Survey&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This is the main source of information on the latest labour market trends throughout Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A selection of some of the latest data is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/data/LFS.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Selected statistics for Calgary and Edmonton are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/data/LFS_cma.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;survey-of-payroll-employment-and-hours&#34;&gt;Survey of Payroll, Employment and Hours&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of the latest SEPH data is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/data/SEPH.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Financing the Future: Options for Long-Run Debt and Spending Sustainability in British Columbia</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bc-fiscal-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bc-fiscal-future/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Government Fiscal Sustainability in Canada After COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/esna_dec2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 09:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/esna_dec2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Queen&#39;s Institute on Trade Policy</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/queens_itp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/queens_itp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
