<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</title>
    <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trevor Tombe on Trevor Tombe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking barriers: How provinces can drive Canada&#39;s prosperity by unlocking trade and labour mobility</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/mli_unilateral/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/mli_unilateral/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Emissions Pricing Hurt Affordability? Quantifying the Effects on Canadian Households</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/irpp_ctax/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/irpp_ctax/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This report investigates the effects of emissions pricing, such as the federal fuel charge or B.C. carbon tax. It focuses on how these policies impact households differently based on their income levels, regions and family types. The analysis is set against the backdrop of rising inflation, particularly between June 2021 and June 2022, when consumer prices rose sharply. One of the key concerns we address is whether emissions pricing significantly contributes to overall cost increases and how government measures, such as rebates, can help ease the financial burden on households.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Aggregate Productivity Effect of Labour and Capital Market Distortions in Canada</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/canada_misallocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/canada_misallocation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Farms to Tables: Quantifying the Effect of Emissions Pricing on Canadian Food Prices</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ctax_food/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ctax_food/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conflict of Interest Disclosure</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/post/conflict/conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/post/conflict/conflict/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aeaweb.org/journals/policies/disclosure-policy&#34;&gt;American Economic Association&lt;/a&gt; urges its members and other economists to disclose potential conflicts of interest through financial support (whether in monetary or non-monetary forms), paid or unpaid positions as officers, directors, or board members of non-profit or for-profit organizations, and if other interested third parties have financial, ideological, or political stakes in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a best efforts disclosure based on the most recent five years of activity. More detail around my past professional affiliations, associations, and activities are listed on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trevortombe.com/files/CV.pdf&#34;&gt;my CV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sources-of-financial-support&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sources of Financial Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the AEA disclosure policy, authors “should identify each interested party from whom he or she has received significant financial support, summing to at least $10,000 in the past three years, in the form of consultant fees, retainers, grants and the like.” I report these below, separating ongoing sources from one-time ad-hoc sources. For completeness, I also report potentially relevant minor sources of financial support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Calgary (2012-Present): amounts disclosed publicly according to Government of Alberta regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Tax Foundation (2020-Present): services related to &lt;em&gt;Finances of the Nation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial support through various grants from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (individually listed on my CV)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funds cover research expenses, primarily graduate student support, and no personal financial benefit results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ad-Hoc (Past Six Years)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McGraw Hill Education (2022-25): textbook revisions and data updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Nova Scotia (2025): consulting services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Chamber of Commerce (2024-25): research paper and data projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macdonald-Laurier Institute (2022; 2024-25): research papers on internal trade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Canada (2022-24): advisory and consulting services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Myers LLP (2022-24): expert advice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of NWT (2024): judicial compensation commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Canada (2020): research and analysis of interprovincial trade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of British Columbia (2020): research contributions to the BC Basic Income Panel (report public)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yukon Government (2017): member of the financial advisory panel (report public)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mount Royal University (2023): undergraduate program review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pearson Canada (2023-24): textbook revisions and data updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C.D. Howe Institute (2020; 2023): research papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macdonald-Laurier Institute (2023): referee report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fraser Institute (2016-2024): referee reports and occasional author fees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2020-21): services to the Ministry of Jobs, Economy and Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Ontario (2021): research and analysis of interprovincial trade costs and policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Queen’s University Institute on Trade Policy (2020): presentation on interprovincial trade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Institute for Fiscal Studies and Democracy (2020): research related to federal transfer arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canadian Economics Association (2019): Vanderkamp Prize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parliamentary Budget Office (2019): one-day course on federal-provincial transfers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government of Alberta (2019): review of internal economic analysis of carbon pricing policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasional author fees for contributions to &lt;em&gt;The Hub&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CBC&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Macleans&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alberta Views&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;affiliations&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Affiliations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current Professional Associations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professor, University of Calgary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director of Fiscal and Economic Policy, The School of Public Policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-Director, Finances of the Nation, &lt;em&gt;Canadian Tax Journal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Associate Editor, &lt;em&gt;Economic Inquiry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-editor, &lt;em&gt;Canadian Public Policy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, The University of Calgary Faculty Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, Board of Trustees, Universities Academic Pension Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, The Alberta Gambling Research Institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member, Canadian Economics Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member, American Economics Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Affiliations and Appointments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Editorial Advisor, &lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Economics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Board Member, ActiveCITY Calgary (2019-20)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the C.D. Howe COVID-19 Crisis Business Continuity and Trade Working Group (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the Government of Alberta Market Access Task Force (2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of the Calgary Chamber of Commerce Municipal Election Advisory Team (2017)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;additional-disclosures&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Disclosures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asset Disclosure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various equity and bond holdings, largely within broadly-diversified exchange traded funds. Minor holdings of individual corporate equities within the Canadian financial and energy sectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Activity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am not a member of any political party at any level of government. Occasional (unpaid) advice and analysis has been provided to individual candidates, office holders, or staff on an ad-hoc basis representing the full spectrum of political parties in Alberta and Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right to Review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No organization has a right to review or edit my published work, except when they acted as the publisher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Partners in Prosperity: How the Canada-U.S. Trade Relationship Goes Beyond Buying and Selling</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/chamber_trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/chamber_trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The importance of the United States as a trading partner for Canada is widely recognized here, but the significance of Canada as a trading partner for the U.S. is often overlooked south of the border. While U.S. trade comprises a larger share of Canada&amp;rsquo;s GDP compared to the reverse, this perspective doesn&amp;rsquo;t fully capture the economic interdependence of the two countries. This report provides a comprehensive look at the complexities of this relationship and the role of trade policy in both countries&amp;rsquo; productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roadblocks ahead: Internal barriers to trade in Canada&#39;s truck transportation sector </title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/mli_trucks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/mli_trucks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Canada&amp;rsquo;s truck transportation sector faces significant economic and legal challenges due to internal trade barriers. These barriers, which include varying regulations across provinces, add approximately 8.3 percent to freight rates, thereby inflating business costs and reducing overall productivity in the economy. This report discusses the potential for a Mutual Recognition Agreement (MRA) under the Canadian Free Trade Agreement (CFTA) as a way to alleviate these obstacles, thereby enhancing economic integration and boosting Canada&amp;rsquo;s productivity and real GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal trade barriers in trucking not only increase the direct costs of shipping goods across provincial lines but also contribute to broader economic inefficiencies. By requiring businesses to navigate a patchwork of provincial regulations, these barriers limit the overall market efficiency and raise prices for consumers. The report finds that eliminating these barriers could lead to significant economic gains across Canada, with the potential to increase national GDP and reduce regional income disparities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tackle the trade barriers, the report proposes that provinces and territories adopt MRAs, which would allow different provincial standards to be recognized under a unified national framework. This approach aims to preserve space for diversity in provincial regulations while ensuring that goods and services can flow more freely across borders. This method may be less burdensome than full regulatory harmonization, which requires provinces to agree on uniform standards. Robust federal-provincial-territorial policy networks make truck transportation an ideal domain in which to implement MRAs. Their implementation here would showcase MRAs&amp;rsquo; effectiveness as a tool that might be viable for tackling other internal trade barriers that the CFTA&amp;rsquo;s Regulatory Reconciliation and Cooperation Table (RCT) is studying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report also discusses the historical context and evolution of these interprovincial barriers, noting that despite the liberalization efforts following the 1995 intergovernmental Agreement on Internal Trade, many regulatory obstacles have persisted. These include differences in acceptable truck sizes and weights, permitting obligations, safety standards, and licencing requirements, which complicate the free movement of goods and services across the country. The paper also examines case studies from other jurisdictions, such as the United Kingdom, where similar barriers were successfully reduced, to highlight the potential benefits of reform. These examples provide a roadmap for Canada, suggesting that modest, strategic adjustments to technical regulations could lead to substantial economic and environmental benefits, including reduced carbon emissions and lower transportation costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support its economic analysis, the report uses data from Statistics Canada and a detailed model of Canada&amp;rsquo;s economy that maps the interconnections between sectors and provinces. It quantifies the impact of trade barriers not just on the trucking industry but across the entire economy. By applying this model, the report illustrates how reducing trade barriers could benefit all provinces, but especially those with lower incomes, thereby addressing some of the existing economic inequalities in Canada. Specifically, we estimate that the gain from removing these internal barriers to be approximately $1.6 billion annually. The report also identifies materially larger gains for smaller and lower-income provinces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the report advocates for strategic policy reforms under the CFTA to reduce internal trade barriers in the truck transportation sector. By adopting a flexible approach through mutual recognition agreements, Canada can enhance its economic unity and unlock significant growth potential, making a strong case for regulatory reform as a catalyst for broader economic improvements. These changes have the potential not only to increase GDP but also to contribute to a more equitable economic landscape across the provinces.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Alberta Pension Advantage? A Quantitative Analysis of a Separate Provincial Plan</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/app/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/app/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Bonds to Banknotes: Central Banking and Public Finances in Canada</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bonds_banknotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/bonds_banknotes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rise, Stall, or Fall: The Key Drivers Behind Inflation&#39;s Path in Canada</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/inflation_fall/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/inflation_fall/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>El efecto de los shocks energeticos en las economias nacionales (The Effect of Energy Shocks on National Economies)</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/energy_shocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/energy_shocks/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paid in Full, Again? Using Alberta&#39;s Windfall Revenues to Eliminate Provincial Debt</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ab_debt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/ab_debt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Our debt is dead,&amp;rdquo; declared a front-page Calgary Herald headline on July 13, 2004 (Hudes, 2021). The paper was covering a famous event in Alberta&amp;rsquo;s fiscal history: Premier Ralph Klein holding a &amp;ldquo;Paid in Full&amp;rdquo; sign high above his head, marking the end of a 10-year plan to eliminate provincial debt as detailed in Budget 1994. To be clear, Alberta was not literally debt free, but by March 31, 2005, it was projected that the province&amp;rsquo;s Debt Retirement Account would have sufficient assets ($3.5 billion) to fully repay remaining debt as it came due over the coming years (Alberta, 2005). For many, that was close enough. And accounting details aside, Alberta&amp;rsquo;s fiscal turnaround-thanks largely to high resource revenues-was indisputably substantial. Net provincial debt (total debt minus financial assets) declined from nearly 15 percent of GDP in 1994 to less than -5 percent 10 years later (when our financial assets exceeded our debt (Finances of the Nation, 2022)-a 20 percentage-point improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Alberta again has the potential to be debt free within a similar time span. In 2022, resource revenues blew past their previous record highs, which, combined with several years of restrained program spending growth, generated significant fiscal surpluses.  While strong cases can be made for using such surpluses to achieve other objectives, such as saving more within the province&amp;rsquo;s Heritage Fund, the current situation may be one where debt repayments are a uniquely attractive option. For the first time in well over a decade, government borrowing rates exceed the expected return on investment savings. And given mounting global economic and geopolitical risks, the financial gain from lowering debt-in the form of lower interest payments-provides welcome certainty where financial investments do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay discusses some of the key considerations in evaluating debt repayment as an option. It also illustrates a set of fiscal projections for Alberta that suggests eliminating provincial debt is achievable within roughly one decade. Whether one favours this option or not, it should be a critical part of Alberta&amp;rsquo;s fiscal policy conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Chamber of Commerce</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/acc_lunch2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2023 09:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/talk/acc_lunch2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reforming Canada&#39;s federal health-care funding arrangements</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/fiscal-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/fiscal-health/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rise (And Fall?) of Inflation in Canada: A Detailed Analysis of Its Post-Pandemic Experience</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/inflation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/publication/inflation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
