<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Trevor Tombe</title>
    <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Trevor Tombe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.trevortombe.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta Economic Conditions Index</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/eci/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/eci/</guid>
      <description>This index compiles monthly data from a variety of sourses to estimate real-time economic conditions in Alberta. It closely follows the Chicago Fed National Activity Index. These estimates will be periodically updated, and typically come with a two to three month lag before all the necessary monthly data is available from Statistics Canada.
You can download a CSV file of the montly index values here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finances of the Nation</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/fon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/fon/</guid>
      <description>The main site for the project is at the financesofthenation.ca.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alberta&#39;s Fiscal Future</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/ab-fiscal-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/ab-fiscal-future/</guid>
      <description>The Alberta&amp;rsquo;s Fiscal Future (AFF) project is a two-year research/public engagement initiative providing the public and policy makers with in-depth analyses of Alberta&amp;rsquo;s fiscal situation and policy options to address it.
The main site for the project is at the School of Public Policy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations Commission</title>
      <link>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/igrc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.trevortombe.com/project/igrc/</guid>
      <description>There is an urgent need to re-assess federal, provincial and municipal expenditure responsibilities, tax powers, and intergovernmental transfers in Canada to address looming fiscal imbalances. To address these ongoing concerns, a steering committee made up of academics and policy researchers from across Canada has proposed an Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations Commission. An independent team of academic experts and policy practitioners from a variety of disciplines across the country will recommend practical reforms to the system of intergovernmental fiscal relations in Canada.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>